We have reached the domain of troubleshooting
and error handling.
In this section on error handling, we will
explore three types of errors common to Python
code.
As we go through these examples, I hope that
you will develop an eye for spotting problems
in code before they happen or at least know
where to look for errors once they do happen,
as even the best programmers spend about a
third of the time coding and two-thirds of
the time making code work.
The first group of errors to cover is the
group of syntax errors.
Syntax errors in code are like punctuation
and spelling errors in writing.
The difference between the two is that in
programming, syntax errors cause code not
to run, whereas in writing, people might misunderstand
what you write or form conclusions about you
as a writer.
In this 511-syntax file, I have three syntax
errors.
Can you spot them?
Unlike some errors, which occur during the
execution of the program, syntax errors prevent
the code from even being compiled and executed
in the first place.
Python's compiler checks for syntax correctness
before running any code, and a syntax error
will halt this process.
One common syntax error is forgetting the
colon at the end of a block definition, which
is easy to do kfor more experienced programmers
learning Python because most programming languages
use curly brackets to define those blocks.
In contrast, Python uses a colon and then
indentation on the lines part of a block.
We are missing a colon at the end of this
function definition on line 2, so I will add
that colon.
Speaking of indentation, we stressed elsewhere
in this course the importance of keeping spacing
consistent with indents.
Are the indents the same on lines 3 and 4?
No.
That is a syntax error.
I will adjust the indent on line 3 to fix
that syntax error.
Do you see the third syntax error anywhere?
Look at line 6.
We have a mismatch on the open and closed
parentheses.
Another common syntax error involves opening
something, like parentheses or quotation marks,
and not closing them properly.
I will add a closing parenthesis to the end
of line 6, and at this point, the syntax errors
should be fixed.
I will run the code.
Syntactically, the code works, but the print
statement on line 4 did not print.
Though we are covering logic errors in the
next topic, what we see on line 4 is an example
of a logic error.
Lines 3 and 4 are out of order, as, in a function,
once a return statement is coded into the
function, that function is done.
I will reverse the code on those two lines,
rerun the code, and now the code works as
intended.